A Guide to the Edward Everett Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #7572
Edward Everett Collection 1811-1864
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
7572
13 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Deposit [1963 Dec 17] 1964 Jun 3
Item Listing
- Manuscripts
  - "The Influence of Imagination", [1811]; AMsS, 3 p.
    [signature on verso]
  - "Guizot's Washington", ca. 1840; AMs, 4 p.
    [A review sent to John G. Palfrey of
    Life, Correspondence and Writings of Washington Published After the American Ed. and Preceded by an Introduction on the Influence of Washington on the American Revolution
    by Pierre G. Guizot. Comments that Guizot's introduction is valuable to the Americans because it was written by an objective and enlightened foreigner] (incomplete)
- Letters
  - Edward Everett to [Dr. John G. Palfrey?], ca. 1840; ALS, 2 p.
    [Covering letter for AMs of "Guizot's Washington"; mentions George S. Hillard's translation of the Introduction to Guizot's Washington.]
  - Edward Everett to William H. Prescott, 1842 Oct 31; ALS, 4 p.
    [Thanks Prescott for copy of his
    History of the Conquest of Mexico
    mentions that it is not yet published in England; tells of death of his oldest daughter and expresses his deep sense of loss.]
  - Edward Everett to Benjamin Pierce, 1846 Nov 25; ALS, 2 p.
    [Concerns Joseph Henry's and John Romeyn Broadhead's qualifications to be the first Secretary of the Smithsonian; mentions Alexander Dallas Bache and Sir Charles Wheatstone. ]
  - Edward Everett to Epes Sargent, 1847 Feb 24; ALS, 2 p.
    [Thanks Sargent for copy of his
    Songs of the Sea With Other Poems
    . ]
  - Edward Everett to Henry Wadsworth Longfellow, 1847 Mar 9; ALS, 1 p.
    [Requests him to stop by his office before going to class.]
  - Edward Everett to Nathan Appleton, 1853 Nov 7; ALS, 2 p.
    [Requests that William D. Ticknor's and Joshua Bates' letter concerning Boston City Library be returned; mentions William Appleton. ]
  - Edward Everett to L. A. Dimock, 1858 Dec 20; Printed letter w/AN, 1 p. w/env
    [Declines invitation to speak to Young Men's Lecture Association of Westfield, Massachusetts. ]
  - Edward Everett to D. Appleton Company, 1858 Dec 29; ALS, 3 p.
    [Promises to send article on Thomas Dowse and discusses the proposal made by Dr. Palmer for the publication of the "Mount Vernon Papers."]
  - Edward Everett to William A. Wheeler, answer from George Ticknor, 1862 Dec 20; ALS, w/AN 1 p.
    [Praises Wheeler's proposed new work (either
    Dictionary of Noted Names of Fiction
    or
    Concordance to the Poems of Shakespeare
    ); Ticknor notes his agreement with Everett's compliments.]
  - Edward Everett to William A. Wheeler, 1864 Sep 6; ALS, 2 p.
    [Acknowledges receipt of Wheeler's Quarto edition of
    Webster's Dictionary
    , with Supplement: "Explanatory and Pronouncing Vocabulary of the Names of Fictitious Persons and Places"; praises supplement but suggests Joe Miller be added.]
- Miscellaneous
  - Receipt by Edward Everett for map presented by John G. Palfrey, Secretary of State, Commonwealth of Massachusetts, to Law Library, Harvard University, 1847 Aug 26; DS